Guide to the Doris Duke Papers on the Rough Point Residence, 1922-1997 RL.01433
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Doris Duke papers on the Rough Point residence
1922-1997
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke, Doris
RL.01433
7.8 Linear Feet
Rough Point was purchased by James B. Duke in 1922. When Duke passed away in 1925, he left the home to his 12-year-old daughter Doris, subject to Mrs. (Nanaline) Duke's life interest. Although Nanaline Duke continued to spend her summers at Rough Point, in the early 1950s she took up permanent residence in New York City and emptied Rough Point of all its furnishings. It was around this time that Doris Duke once again became a frequent visitor to Newport and turned her attention to renovating and refurnishing the family estate. Upon her death in 1993, Miss Duke bequeathed the estate to the Newport Restoration Foundation with the directive that it be opened to the public as a museum. The collection primarily documents the expenses and daily operations of running, renovating, and maintaining the Rough Point estate, and includes invoices and receipts for repairs and renovations to the residence, correspondence and memoranda relating to routine matters of the residence, expenses, inventories of furniture, fixtures, and other household items, and several appraisals of the residence and its household effects. A majority of the architectural records detail alterations and additions to the Rough Point residence as designed by the Horace Trumbauer firm.
approximately 2,400 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use. Due to the fragility of the Architectural records, The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Doris Duke Papers on the Rough Point Residence were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a donation from the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation in June 2009.
Historical Note
Originally built for Frederick W. Vanderbilt in 1887 in Newport, R.I., Rough Point was purchased by James Buchanan (J.B.) Duke in 1922. Soon thereafter, J.B. turned his efforts to both furnishing and renovating the estate. He hired the Horace Trumbauer firm to assist in renovating the house which was completed in 1924. When Duke passed away a year later, he left the home to his 12-year-old daughter Doris, subject to Mrs. (Nanaline) Duke's life interest. At the time, the housed was appraised for $212,000 without its contents and was considered one of the most fashionable Gilded Age mansions in Newport. Although Nanaline Duke continued to spend her summers at Rough Point, in the early 1950s she took up permanent residence in New York City and emptied Rough Point of all its furnishings. It was around this time that Doris Duke once again became a frequent visitor to Newport and turned her attention to renovating and refurnishing the family estate. Over the years, she purchased arts and antiques for the house and combined them with family treasures. Upon her death in 1993, Miss Duke bequeathed the estate to the Newport Restoration Foundation with the directive that it be opened to the public as a museum.
Collection Overview
The Doris Duke Papers on the Rough Point Residence (formerly RP.4) are part of the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation Historical Archives which were donated to the Duke University Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library by the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation. The collection is arranged into two series: Administrative Records and Architectural Records. It spans the years 1922 to 1997, beginning with invoices and vouchers of furnishings, paintings, and rugs purchased for Rough Point by James Buchanan (J.B.) and Nanaline Duke, and ending with maintenance and general upkeep of the estate after Doris Duke's death in 1993. The collection primarily documents the expenses and daily operations of running, renovating, and maintaining the Rough Point estate, and includes invoices and receipts for repairs and renovations to the residence, correspondence and memoranda relating to routine matters of the residence, expenses, inventories of furniture, fixtures, and other household items, and several appraisals of the residence and its household effects. A majority of the architectural records detail alterations and additions to the Rough Point residence as designed by the Horace Trumbauer firm. The materials in this collection are arranged loosely in chronological order.
Related Material
Duke Family Papers, 1885-1992
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke Family New York Apartments Collection, 1908-1997
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Doris Duke Papers on the Shangri La Residence, 1932-2003
Duke University Archives/David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Newport (R.I.); Architecture -- Designs and plans; Architectural drawing -- United States -- 20th century; Trumbauer, Horace, 1869-1938; Duke, Doris; Duke, Doris
- Administrative Records, 1922-1997
  Scope and Contents note
  Materials in this series include correspondence dating from the 1950s inquiring about Doris Duke's plans for the estate. These letters, addressed to both to Doris Duke and S.L. Hawkins, include suggestions for donating the estate for a Greek orphanage and school, an Episcopalian Girls' School, and a hotel. Also included are documents related to Miss Duke's attempts to lease or rent Rough Point for the long term. The series also consists of appraisals of the estate after Hurricanes Carol and Edna in 1954, invoices for repairs to the interior and exterior of Rough Point, invoices for the purchase and repair of furniture, which includes fabric samples, invoices and vouchers for the purchase and repair of art objects, inventory books documenting the contents of each room of the estate (including color and black and white photographs), and memoranda and newspaper clippings regarding the Cliff Walk at Rough Point.
  Conditions Governing Access note
  RESTRICTED: Access to some folders in Box 1 are restricted and require prior written approval from the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation to view.
  - Measurements for rooms at Rough Point. undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Memoranda and newspaper clippings regarding the Cliff Walk at Rough Point. 1928, c. 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to Doris Duke’s sale of real estate on Lakeview Ave., Newport, R.I., for $15,000 and appraisal in connection with Newport storm loss affecting Rough Point (1954). 1954–1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence relating to property bids on Doris Duke’s Lakeview property and interest in renting Rough Point to Mrs. George Emerson. 1954–1962 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to a variety of day-to-day activities at Rough Point including the rental of the Duke cabana at the spouting Rock Beach Association, appraisal of select personal property (1955) and donation of furniture to St. Georges School. 1955–1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Memoranda and notes regarding installation of draperies and related hardware at Rough Point. Includes estimates and invoices for this work. 1960, 1982–1984 (bulk dates 1983-1984) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and related materials concerning Doris Duke’s erection of 6 ft. tall chain link fences on Cliff Walk. File includes newspaper clippings and discussion by town council. 1961–1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Memoranda and related materials concerning public access on the Cliff Walk which traverses Doris Duke’s property and other matters. 1962–1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, memoranda, and related materials documenting day-to-day activities at Rough Point. 1962–1966 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Memoranda explaining the charges to Ben Reed for the fumigation of Rough Point. December 1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence regarding repairs to roofing, flashing, and masonry work completed at Rough Point by the National Contracting Company. August 25, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Memoranda regarding maintenance and repairs at Rough Point. 1974–1975, 1977, 1980, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Instructions for using adhesive backings used on fragile textiles. Includes some of these backings. 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Memorandum from Jenny at Rough Point to Chandi Heffner regarding an employee at Rough Point, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Access restricted
  - Correspondence sent to various recipients informing them that Miss Duke was traveling frequently and would be unable to meet with them. 1980 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letter from John Nutt to Doris Duke apologizing for the way he spoke to her. August 23, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Memoranda and manuals regarding the repair to the heating system at Rough Point. 1986 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Memoranda regarding the need for photographs of various items at Rough Point for the RP Inventory Books. October 18, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Memoranda from the DBO regarding insurance claims for Rough Point dogs Kimo, Chairman Mou, and Starbuck. 1988, 1993–1995 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Memoranda regarding grooming of Rough Point dogs. 1989–1991 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Memoranda regarding repair work done to the Swimming Pool at Rough Point by the architectural designer Steven Laurin. 1991 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Memoranda, specifications, and invoice pertaining to the Swimming Pool at Rough Point. 1991 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Memoranda and correspondence with the Coastal Resources Management Council, Wake Field, R.I., including an amended Permit for repair work along the Cliff Walk at Rough Point. 1992 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Memoranda and notes from the DBO inquiring about obtaining a copy of the plot plan of the Rough Point residence. 1992 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Memoranda from Phil Mello to Bernard Lafferty and the Duke Business Office regarding work repairs done at Rough Point. 1993–January 1994 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Memoranda and notes from the Newport Animal Hospital regarding care for the Rough Point dogs. 1993, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Memoranda, faxes, and newspaper clippings sent from the DBO to Phil Mello regarding Bernard Lafferty and the settlement of the Estate of Doris Duke. 1994 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Memoranda from Phil Mello to Bernard Lafferty regarding the repair of the Ballroom wallpaper at Rough Point. 1994 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Memoranda, faxes, and newspaper clippings sent from the Duke Business Office to Phil Mello regarding Bernard Lafferty and the Estate of Doris Duke. 1995 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Memoranda from the Duke Business Office from Patrick Lerch to Phil Mello at Rough Point regarding communication with fellow employees as well as public relations with the press and legal counsel. 1996 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Rough Point stationary. c. 1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Invoices and vouchers of purchases of furnishings, paintings, and rugs for Rough Point. 1922–1925, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Invoices for furniture purchased for Rough Point. 1941, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Invoices for three Steinway pianos for Rough Point. April 1953 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Invoices for purchase and repairing of chandeliers at Rough Point. 1954, 1959, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Invoices for repairs made to carpets and rugs at Rough Point. 1955–1990 (bulk dates 1980-1984) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Invoices for roofing and chimney repairs made at Rough Point. 1956–1960, 1968, 1970, 1977, 1981–1982 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Invoices for paintings, portraits, and frames at Rough Point. Includes invoices for restoration work performed on the Hoppner portrait of “Lady Charles Fitzroy” and the Duc D’Alencon’s “Francois Clovet.” 1956, 1963, 1965, 1969, 1971–1972, 1983–1984 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Invoices for purchasing and repairing windows at Rough Point. Includes waterproofing repairs made to Rough Point. 1957, 1961, 1966–1968, 1971–1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Invoices for carpentry and construction work at Rough Point. 1957, 1960–1962, 1964, 1966, 1971–1972, 1981–1982 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Invoices for installation of a fence at Rough Point. 1957, 1960–1964, 1969–1972, 1980–1983 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Invoices for construction repairs, electrical work, plumbing, heating, and refrigeration work performed at Rough Point. 1957–1960, 1966, 1971, 1975, 1981, 1983–1984, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Invoices for plumbing, heating, and masonry repairs made at Rough Point. 1957, 1962, 1969, 1974–1979, 1980–1984, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Invoices for repairs performed on lamps, lanterns, and torcheres at Rough Point. 1959. 1971, 1982, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Invoices for a Vulcan stove purchased by Doris Duke. Also includes invoices for repair work performed on the shutters at Rough Point. Repair work authorized by Mrs. J.B. Duke. 1960, 1966, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Invoice for tile work conducted in the Kitchen at Rough Point. 1961 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Invoices for tables at Rough Point. Includes purchase of Jardinière Ming Turquoise table with Teak stand, and Early 19th c. table, and TV tables. 1961, 1963, 1967, 1969, 1972, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Invoices for hanging of drapes at Rough Point. Includes freight shipment receipts for the shipment of rugs and tapestries to Rough Point. 1961, 1969, 1973, 1981–1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Invoices for repairs done on a quilt at Rough Point. 1963, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Invoices for an iron, sewing machine, and vacuum cleaner from Rough Point. 1964, 1966, 1972, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Invoices for lawn maintenance at Rough Point. 1964, 1966, 1972, 1981, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Invoices and memos regarding repairs and installation of a new boiler at Rough Point. 1966, 1979, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Invoices for electrical repair work performed at Rough Point. 1968–1969, 1971–1973, 1981–1984 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Invoices for chairs, benches, and sofas located at Rough Point. 1969, 1971, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Invoices and memoranda regarding the restoration of tapestries at Rough Point. 1970–1971 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Invoices for repair work on windows, doors, and ceilings at Rough Point. 1971–1972 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Invoices for repair work performed at Rough Point. Includes some repairs done at Duke Farms as well. 1972 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Invoices for furniture reupholstery work performed on chaise lounges, cushions, and curtains at Rough Point. Work repairs authorized by Leon Amar and Doris Duke. 1972, 1977, 1980, 1983–1984 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Invoices, with fabric samples, for upholstery on furnishings at Rough Point. Some purchased by LADD Interiors. 1973–1979 (1 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Invoices, with fabric samples, for upholstery on furnishings at Rough Point. Some purchased by LADD Interiors. 1973–1979 (2 of 3) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Invoices, with fabric samples, for upholstery on furnishings at Rough Point. Some purchased by LADD Interiors. 1973–1979 (3 of 3) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Invoices for repairs to the sewer system at Rough Point. Also includes invoices for paint for Miss Duke’s Bedroom and other rooms at Rough Point. 1973, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Invoices for brushes, powdered polish, and canvas chests, which were used to conduct repair work on silver, porcelain, and furniture at Rough Point. 1975–1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Invoices for purchases made from LADD Interiors. 1975–1980 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Tax bills for Rough Point. 1977–1984 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Invoices for repairs made on tapestries at Rough Point. 1978–1983 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Invoice and memoranda for the repair of a 19th century Chinese bird painting. Includes photos. 1980–1981 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Receipt for paint for the 3rd Floor Apartment at Rough Point. 1983 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Invoices for repairs performed on a truck at Rough Point. 1983–1984 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Invoices for repairs performed on vehicles at Rough Point. 1984 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Invoices from and payments made to Richard Caldwell for bookbinding repair work. 1986–1988 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Invoices for and payments made to Christopher Foster Glassworks for repairs made to stained glass windows at Rough Point. 1987 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Invoices for fence repairs at Rough Point. 1987 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Invoices for painting restoration work performed by H.R. Finn Gallery. 1987 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Invoices from and payments made to Baker Golf Cars for repairs performed on golf cars from the Rough Point estate. 1987 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Invoices from and payments made to Charles Von Nostitz for conservation repairs made to paintings at Rough Point. 1987 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Invoices from and payments made to H.R. Finn Gallery for conservation repairs made to watercolors at Rough Point. 1987 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Invoices, proposal, and memo regarding the installation of a security system at Rough Point. 1987 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Estimate for new slipcovers on sofas and chairs in the Salon and Sun Room at Rough Point. Includes a fabric sample. September 2, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Invoices for preservation work performed by Costikiyan on carpets at Rough Point. 1989 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Invoice for lighting repair work performed by Times Square Lighting at Rough Point. 1991 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Proposal and memoranda for the installation of a new oil burner at Rough Point. 1960 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Inventory of chairs at Rough Point. undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Appraisal of furnishings and contents located at Rough Point at the time of J.B. Duke’s death. December 2, 1925 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - List of items shipped from Rough Point to Porfirio Rubirosa in Paris. August 1948–September 1948 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Inventory of furniture left at Rough Point for auction. 1954 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Inventory and invoices for furniture and rug purchases. Includes invoices for purchases made at Parke-Bernet Galleries, Inc. Also includes purchase of a Bible for Miss Duke, noted as “personal” on the invoice (March 14, 1974). 1954–1984 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Inventory sheets, notes, and invoices for purchases and repairs of items at Rough Point. Included in these sheets are invoices for a bust, tapestry repair, and services rendered for securing stained-glass items. 1954, 1968, 1971, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Inventory cards for silver and fine art at Rough Point. c. 1958, 1971, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - List of vendors who performed work at Rough Point and the costs for these jobs. May 17, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Memoranda relating to the use of “in-out checklists” at Rough Point to inventory items and their move within the house as well as to other Doris Duke homes. 1971, 1976, 1988–1989 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Inventories of objects at Rough Point as well as lawn equipment at RP. File includes related memoranda. 1972–1983 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Appraisal for Oriental and European rugs at Rough Point, conducted by John H.Kazanjian. April 1974–October 1974 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Appraisal reports completed by J.A. Lloyd Hyde for furniture, home furnishings, paintings, and tapestries at Rough Point. 1974–1975 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Inventory of lamps and tables at Rough Point. 1977, 1981, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Inventory cards for the silver collection at Rough Point. c. 1978 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Surveys and repairs of tables at Rough Point and Duke Farms by Phil Mello. 1978–1982 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Includes weekly reports and time sheets from Betsy Ray and Judy Boss, Estate Managers of Rough Point. Also includes evaluation and estimates for repairs to wall at Rough Point, 1979–1981 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Christie’s catalog record for a George II walnut and gilt mirror. c. 1980s (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Inventory cards and related materials concerning objects at Rough Point. 1980, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Weekly work report from Judy Boss. February 1981–April 1981 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Weekly reports from John Nutt, Rough Point. Includes Duke Farms memoranda about gassing vehicles. 1981 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Maintenance report from Phil Mello. November 29, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Inventory, In/Out sheets that note physical location of various furniture in and out of Rough Point. 1988–1989 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Inventories of Shangri La, Rough Point, and Falcon Lair. Includes 1988–1989 inventory of the silver in the Butler’s Pantry at Rough Point. 1988–1989, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Inventory of carpets, rugs, and furniture at Rough Point. Includes invoices for repair work done to some of these items by Costikiyan. 1989 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Weekly work reports from Phil Mello to U.S. Trust Co. with an additional copy sent to Marianne Bowles of the DBO. 1993 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Weekly report from Phil Mello to Bernard Lafferty. May 27, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Weekly work reports from Phil Mello to U.S. Trust Co. with an additional copy sent to Marianne Bowles of the DBO. 1994 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence related to Cliff Walk bridge and pool at Rough Point, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Invoices of Rough Point Pool Project, 1991 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Weekly work reports from Phil Mello to U.S. Trust Co. with an additional copy sent to Marianne Bowles of the DBO. 1995 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Inventory sheets for items at Rough Point. Includes Black Books, items belonging to Walker P. Inman, Jr. and Bernard Lafferty. 1995–1998 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Weekly work reports from Phil Mello to U.S. Trust Co. with an additional copy sent to Marianne Bowles of the DBO. 1998 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Articles regarding craftsmanship and bathroom fixture repair. 1978, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Rough Point Restoration Proposal, Universal Restoration, 1970 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Newport – Inventory of Furniture and Equipment. 1922–1924 (Box 8)
  - Rough Point Photo Inventory Book - Main Entrance, Music Room, Great Hall, Stair Hall, 1989 (Box 9)
  - Rough Point Photo Inventory Book - 2nd Floor Hallway, Ballroom, 1989 (Box 9)
  - Rough Point Photo Inventory Book - Yellow Room, Striped Bedroom, Green Room, 1989 (Box 10)
  - Rough Point Photo Inventory Book - Butler's Pantry, Silver, China, 1989 (Box 10)
  - Rough Point Photo Inventory Book - Morning Room, Miss Duke's Bedroom, 1989 (Box 11)
  - Rough Point Photo Inventory Book - Tapestry Room, Black and White Room, Red Bedroom, Pink Bedroom, 1989 (Box 11)
  - Rough Point Photo Inventory Book - Powder Room, Mens Room, Solarium, Solarium Terrace, Dining Room, Blue Bedroom, 1989 (Box 12)
  - Changes in Newport Inventory. Includes invoices for art and furnishings purchased, 1955-1979 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Rough Point Detail of Bills for Gas Heating, Original Costs and Subsequent Repairs and Servicing Costs, 1961-1973 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Invoices for painting and chandelier restoration. Includes black and white photographs, 1975 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and memoranda relating to business activities at Rough Point, 1987-1993 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Invoices for pool project at Rough Point estate, 1991 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Final treatment report, "Conservation of Chinese Wallpaper, Rough Point Residence, Doris Duke Estate, Newport, RI", written by Susan Nash, 1994 Feb (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Rough Point, Dogs Birth Dates, undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Photograph inventory, Ballroom, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Photograph inventory, Ballroom, 1984 (Box 13, Folder 9)